so this is from the angut nikaya book of
the free because there are these three kinds
free because there are these three kinds
of Purity what fre purity of body speech
and mind and what is purity of body it
is when a b abstains from killing living
creatures stealing and in celibacy this
is called purity of body and what is
purity of speech it's when a big web
stains from false malicious harsh and
trivial speech this is called purity of
speech and what is purity of mind it's
when a biku when there is sensual desire
internally understands there is sensual
desire internally for me when there is
no sensual desire intern
he understands there is no sensual
desire internally for me he understands
how unisen sensual desire arises how
Arisen sensual desire is abandoned and
how abandoned sensual desire doesn't
arise again in the
future and then it goes on for the other
hindrances in the same way perversion
second hindrances second Hance indolence
and Lethy then restlessness and anxiety
and also doubt then there also verse so
this discourse concludes these are the
three kinds of Purity purity of body
purity of speech and undefiled purity of
Mind clean and doubt with Purity he has
washed away all evil they
say now one thing that stands out to me
here is concerning the purity of mind
let's take this first Hance for example
it says what is purity of mind
when there is desire sensual desire
internally he understands there is
sensual desire internally for me but
then when there is no sensual desire
internally he understands there's no
sensual desire internally for me and
both are defined here as
Purity how's that possible How can there
be Purity when somebody understands that
there's still sensual desire internally
what would you
say yeah so um
that's what I think we sort of touched
on that in some of the previous talks
about patient endurance and so on the
recognition is that that
underlies that principle is
that fundamentally
fundamentally
um impurity or defilement arises on
account of your choices it never arises
by accident and and the five hindrances
are technically something that
isn't up to you whether they're there or
not if you for example if you haven't
been in
seclusion even
for uh those things would still be
uh those things would still be
there those hes yeah so that's why some
of the sutas for example would say um
well that's it's not obviously the same
thing because when craving is not there
you cannot say it's the same thing
anymore no but the let's say the shap
the shape or the the the shell of those
things uh would be essentially the same
thing kind of like dried up but it's the
same thing sometimes s would say like a tree
thing sometimes s would say like a tree
with the root cut off but like the tree
is still there standing but dead so um
the point is that even for them like
another Su would for example say if
aarun is not
uh detached externally from things like
Fame gain
popularity and sort of worldly
engagements that are not against the
precepts uh but you know happen as a
result of circumstance or whatever they
will lose their Pleasant abiding here
and now and even in some cases which is
a another way of saying they will lose
their abiding free from these five
things and in some cases um stories in
the sutas the the Buddha would um like
refuse to be visited by people who
wanted to just bring offerings to kind
of just Without Really any interest in
the dama because he knew that that would
result in unnecessary engagements that
would basically make his mind more
liable to those things and it's not that
you know it might sound then as if oh he
was craving to to maintain samadi or
something and it says there uh whoever
cannot get at ease at will that pleasure
renunciation they would they would uh
agree to these things but I won't and
that sounds like oh he's attached to his
Sam or something but uh the point is
like no
um in itself the principle
of uh preferring pleasure and avoiding
pain something that's embedded into the
Aggregates it's not in and of itself
self craving craving is another layer
that's added to that let's put it that
way so the point here then is that yes
inevitably even like no matter how
diligent you are how uh perfectly um
committed to the to the path you are
there will be times when those things
will be there in your mind and if it
were a matter of not having those things
in order to be pure it would mean that
basically you could lose your arship and
that's impossible that's what I just
mentioned that says an Aran to lose
their Pleasant dividing it says also the
unshakable liberation of mind that
cannot be lost and that's why it's
called unshakable yeah and that's what
this is describing meaning the
understanding of your mind even when it
is in such a States means that you will
be unable to make choices on account of
sensual desire on account of ill will
and because of that I mean technically
you use again you use the same name but
in an ordinary person those states are
made what they are because they act out
of them that's why then when the acting
out has been completely destroyed you
can't call them hindrances anymore but
in of itself like it's kind of the same
thing but that's why it requires nuance
and and caveats need to be made because
otherwise people think also you're
saying Anar still has UNH wholesome
States but the thing is no the state
like the whole point I mean this this is
exactly what aapan understands and
that's why they're able to cultivate the
path as a s to say uh he he understands
that the defilements are gratuitous like
they're kind of um he says they they uh
flow in on the mind and so means states
and your actions and account of it and
your intentions and account of it are
two separate things yes which is the
same thing is saying unpleasant feeling
is one thing and craving is another
thing and it sounds kind of oh yeah of
course that makes sense but seeing that
concretely means seeing the four noble
truths and it's the same with this like
seeing how you can have these mental
states without there being any craving
if you understand that that would
already be stream entry and that's why
um in the as well it says in the mind
contemplation section it says how how is
aiku uh abide uh maintain the
perspective of the Mind simultaneously
with the mind and it says um doesn't say
when he has an a passionate mind he gets
rid of it but he stops thinking it says
he knows a passionate mind as a
passionate mind he knows an averse mind
as an averse mind and so on to list all
these possibilities and permutations and
at the end it says one who abides like
this abides disengaged not taking up
anything in the world yeah so of course
if you if you continue abiding in that
way like with this recognition of
passionate mind as passionate mind and
so on you're essentially
um that's what's taking your mind away
from that but that's in and of itself
it's it's not that it's UNH wholesome
for those states to be there if there's
no ignorance like that's why as as to
say Anar has finish their work in other
words they don't even need to practice
amadi anymore so but yes if if and that
and that's what a trainee has to do they
have to maintain perspective of these
states and genuinely try to free their
mind from these states so that they can
you know abide in janas and then become
an our hunt so that they won't even need
to to uh have their minds in that in
that uh uh internally purified State
anymore yeah so that is part of the
understanding of how unisen sensual
desire arises and how and how aisen
sensual desire is abandoned that's the
difference there yeah and and obviously
then the the the thing to clarify is
like you will never be able to have that
knowledge and that type of Purity if you
haven't beforehand cultivated
the freedom from like completely freedom
from sensual desire freedom from
aversion freedom from these things which
is always temporary which is yes if you
haven't practiced that like practicing
that is what enables you to like when
you come back to the normal sort of like
dealing with stuff and and movement of
the mind and so on all of the wrong
assumptions and ignorance and and
craving can't be there even though you
went back to to Baseline quote unquote
mhm yeah now there is some ambiguity
here about the words mental and mind
because earlier you said these states
states quote unquote could still even
arise for the Arad right and it talks
about sensuality and the other
hindrances internally but then you start
it out by saying no no hindrances is
when you act out but we should clear up
that acting out is by Body by speech and
by mind yeah so there is also a m acting
out which is on the level of
mono that we should separate from Chinta
which is also mind being affected by
sensuality aversion and so on because
otherwise if you don't make that
distinction now then it's very easy to
fall into the view that acting out just
pertains to body and speech and then it
becomes still a jumble on the mental
level and you can easily take a long
turn there yeah so uh that's the thing
if it's mono so um Mano is basically
your you could say it's your
um that's where your intention is and
that's why that's why there's that first
verse from the dam that says whoever
acts with a polluted mind mono yeah it
says that's the source of all suffering
like a like a like a the wheel of the
cart follows the
the so that's Mano because that's what's
your responsibility is but like that's
let's say you know you have your
external environment like you know
what's happening around you in the world
and then you have your internal
environment which is your
TI and uh your actions by Mano will
influence that ex that internal
environment as well your CH just like it
can influence your external external
environment but uh like I said to some
extent that internal environment is not
completely in your control like it's
sometimes you will have to the the most
uh sort of
uh direct obstacle to samadi is lack of
seclusion and even if everything else is
perfectly uh in your control at some
point you will have to abandon seclusion
and that means you will lose your s
because as it to say uh the first J is
like sensation of speech so as soon as
you start speaking you're back to yes
back to the normal kind of um State and
that's why restraining speech is so
important as well but um that so because
it's it's always connected with your
intention um like I said before it is always in
um like I said before it is always in
your control but the problem is um
there's this natural assumption again
because of not being able to clearly see
that difference between J and mono which
is I mean if you can see that that's
already uh essentially that is the Right
View M um if you can see that because by
the way that's how you see wholesome and
UNH wholesome like you know most most of
people would just assume if I have the
inclination towards um you know sensual
thoughts or or aers thoughts in my mind
that in itself means I have craving or
or I am doing something UNH wholesome
and therefore I have to get rid of it
but no it's the inclination is there but
you always have like a Second Step there
that you yourself make in relation to
that inclination and see it's the same
Principle as with bodily and verbal
action uh you don't uh cut your hands
off so that you can't steal anymore a
bigu doesn't castrate himself so that he
doesn't engage in in celibacy you don't
you know cut your tongue off so that you
can't lie and and uh you know have har
harsh speech you simply don't do it even
though the possibility for it is still
there and it's exactly the same
principle on a mental level just
obviously it's much more subtle you have
the possibility to engage in the sensal
desire because your mind is in a state
of sensal Desire that internal
environment is there but you choosing to
then um attend to sensal objects through
that sensal desire that's that's a
that's your own choice and that is very
than wholesome starts yeah exactly so um
so that means that just to be very clear
now when the Mind CH is affected by
sensuality as long as one doesn't
decides to act out by Body speech or
mind mono then this counts as purity of
mind on the CH level yeah and if you're
in seclusion and and everything well you
wouldn't even be able to tell what
action by Mano is if you haven't
developed the The Graduate training and
seclusion but um it would just be all a
jumbo and you would think you're
purifying Mano when in reality you're
just trying to get rid of your CH and so
on but
um then when when you have that
recognition then maintaining that purity
of Mano will in in return calm down the
CH but that's always temporary yeah so
now somebody finds so suppose somebody
has some understanding of this
distinction they see CH is affected by
sensuality but now simultaneously
there's also a sensual thought presence
which is on the Man level M then
not if there is well actually that's a
good point um the sutas always talk
about abandoning UNH wholesome thoughts
via and there's a whole there's these
two famous suas in maik MAA 19 MAA 20
where it talks about oh the monk is
practicing diligently and the sensal
thoughts adverse thoughts arise and then
he gets rid of them obliterates them
destroys them and see because people
don't see that distinction between Mano
and chah mhm what they're really doing
they're not just stopping at the
threshold of their intention they're
going further and they're trying to
destroy the entire chitt as well they
don't see like again to give the example
with body and speech they're not just
choosing not to take the object they're
cutting their hands off and and
obviously they don't recognize that
because it's a very subtle kind of um
distinction distinction but uh
so only when you're able to see that
division completely kind of a um
irreconcilable division the division
between Mano and chah between your
intention and that internal environment
that pressures you to intend only when
you can see that division you're able to
actually purify your mind and that's why
um like yeah but purify mind which is to
purify J yeah well both like you you're
able to cuz see if you don't see uh this
distinction that's why the Su say you
cannot purify your mind accidentally not
like suddenly something happened and my
mind is pure either of them yeah whether
it's man or chitt like I just had this
experience and now it's pure because see
if you don't see that distinction on
some level you'll be interfering with ch
and trying to get rid of it and that in
itself is through Mano and un wholesome
action out of CR
right so so um not so it's not even um
sure you can say it's acting out but
it's not on the same level as just body
and speech where like any random person
can you just tell him hey stop doing
that and he can here it's like if you
don't see the division or the that sort
of line where your action begins and the
mental state is there on its own
anything you do is acting out of the
mental state yeah so then we that's why
like with ignorance there is activities
simultaneous like there is
like there is
action like the whole like the
fundamental like with dependent
origination right but about that's where
it starts yeah so activities here is
Again by Body speech M exactly yeah yes
so again J is let's say there's a one
notices a verion on on that background
mind level
um then if one says that shouldn't be
there and I'm going to do something in
order to get rid of that aversion on
that jeta level that acting out would be
the hindrance of aversion not the
presence of the Avers CH yeah ironically
yeah so so actually I don't know if I
finished what I was saying when I
mentioned the suas uh before about
obliterating thoughts oh yes so that is
valid like it's true it's genuinely
saying you have to obliterate these
thoughts but that's referring to your
intention in regard to these mental
States in other words like like you know
somebody's um there's a there's a
current going in a certain direction and
now you swim with it that's what you
abandon but you don't like the current
is not in your control to begin with
well in directly now of course like
that's what the suas are saying actually
when the the monk has been purifying his
thoughts in this way for a while then
the mind it says internally as well the
Mind settles down in other words there's
not even now the inclination to make
those choices in other words the CH
itself has calmed down mhm and that's
that's what eventually uh that you you
want that to happen in order to
cultivate samadi um so in know but again
if you don't see the distinction between
the two you'll be oh yeah I'm going to
obliterate my thoughts I'm going to get
rid of them but what you're really doing
is you're fighting with your mental
state and that's when it becomes like
like as we say management managing your
internal environment in in your mind in
the same way you're trying to manage
things out there in the world and that
implicitly carries a notion that that
internal environment is
yours so that's that like even if you're
contemplating oh this is not mine this
is not mine to get rid of those thoughts
you're implying that it's yours because
otherwise like how why would you be
trying to exert control over something
if you know that it's not yours yeah now
what did you mean that when you say
internal just because these distinctions
right so
um so
CH can be purified but that only happens
indirectly as a result of having the
mental Purity on the Mano level
sustaining it yeah to to sustain that
yeah and now you brought up maim 19 and
20 because that those discourses talk
about ways to correctly deal with
thoughts which is on the level of Mano
yeah on the you could say on the
external level not external when you say
doesn't mean like related to the world
or other people means like that level
where your intention is involved in this
context whereas internally is a level
that's kind of not really in your
control but it is fed that's why this is
to say um you starve the
hindrances uh so you can never complet
you can never directly get rid of them
you can uh abandon them you can abandon
them completely and that's what the
janas are but it's never by you getting
rid of it it's by ceasing to provide the
fuel which is through the minor level
your intention it's like a vicious
circle the pressure to act is there you
act out that increases the pressure to
act which makes you act more and then it
becomes like so the environment that you
put you kind of adding stuff to that
internal environment which is then
making you want to act more and more the
opposite is true now so um it's not that
you're fully helpless against it so if
you learn how to stop acting out through
what it to do what it's pressuring you
to do it starts to Cal down as well and
then they will be not even a inclination
to do that and that's when that's when
the minus actually come yeah
now again in terms of understanding the
right way of not acting out right
there's no acting out on the level of CH
which is what we've called internal that
we've now clarified but then there is
the no like the internal level is not
where the acting out happens no the
external I mean this doesn't expli call
it that way but you can say external
it's like um so this there's this thing
here and then qu and quote here and then
you run with it yes that's why it's kind
of like a direction from internal to
external you kind of express it in some
way let's say even not in the world but
through your even like your internal
thinking you express the pressure in the
same way like when you're pressured to
as it says to to steal or to do
something kind of like you go and do it
yeah so internal the inter internal
Dimension is the one that's not really
up to you uhhuh as we say yes but then
mono mind is not that is you in that
context yeah and so then it is up to you
to not act out of un wholesome yeah but
now suppose that on that level where you
are which is the mono mind level there
is let's say a thought of aversion MH or
a thought of Cruelty then are you saying
then the practice is also to recognize
that and to endure those thoughts as
well basically to not welcome and
Enlighten them but also to not overso
the mark and go to the other way and
start getting rid of them but is it then
just a question of observing those
thoughts and waiting for them to go or
because this is how we get into to the
majima 1920 because practically speaking
this is at some point where the practice
has to take place yeah so the thing
there is if you start calling it
thoughts that I mean that's the way we
use the word in English it kind of
refers to both active and passive
whereas in the v always refers to active
like is is something you're doing yes
and dama like phenomenon is something
that arises on its own uhhuh so in this
case you could say you have
Damas like mental images you could say
or or kind of subtle sort
of waves or energies if you want to call
it that of a virgin MH but if there is a
thought of a verion AA of a version that
mean that already involves intention and
that you don't you don't have to endure
that you have to get rid of it yeah like
so that shouldn't be there to begin with
in other words you have the the pressure
but you're not acting out of it that's
what that's what it means to get rid of
your ruas so then
um uh yeah that's why that's what
they're saying you obliterate the
thoughts like as soon as they arise you
shouldn't tolerate even for a second MH
initially obviously you will be trying
to do that and you'll be mistake
mistaking the vakas for the state of
mind and you'll be kind of trying to get
rid of one while you're proliferating
the other and and everything will be a
muddle but if you have have been
developing the prerequisite of graduate
training you will get to see that um cuz
like if you can't even restrain your
more course choices by body and speech
there's just no chance that you'll be
able to see this thing that's like you
know if these if these are 4x4 cm in
size this is like you know 1 nmet of
diameter so um you you just won't be
able to do it so um the thing is uh
yeah but if you if you keep at it
eventually like again not kind
of continuously questioning yourself not
assuming like oh I'm already doing it
properly eventually you get to see oh so
actually it's in a way it's kind of
effortless I don't need to like
constantly be straining myself to to not
act out by mind like I don't need to be
straining myself not to steal something
I just need to
do nothing basically and then that's
what that's what that's what it becomes
like it becomes you realize actually the
whole kind of uh agitation that you had
to do something to get rid of these
thoughts to management to think the
opposite to do this all of that was
rooted in the same pressure in the end
but um like I said it won't be perfect
but eventually you'll get to see oh even
that actually is an action by Mono and
that's then when you um when you're able
to as a it says there like you fully
understand how the Arisen hindrance came
to be MH how the unisen hindrance
doesn't arise in the future um how to
abandon the Arisen hindrance means like
you you will not be conf conflating
anymore uh what's actually your
responsibility with with that which has
resent on its own which means all that
sort of confusion and agitation and
viation and what do I do none of that
will be there which means even when you
when you have no samadi you perfectly
know how to get it back and uh like
nobody can stop you basically so so in
in other words you wouldn't be suffering
it's like you know how the S say it's
like uh kind of impris the hindrances
are imprisoners of the Mind well imagine
yeah you're still in the prison and
you're still in the prison cell but you
have the key for the door so it's like
yes you technically you're in the prison
but not really so that's how it is when
and like that's what that purity of mind
like even though technically the same
state is there the fact that you know
perfectly how to get out of it means
you're actually not uh enslaved by it in
the way you were
before have you cleared up this
distinction between Mano and T you think
like practically speaking we're not
interested in academic distinctions but
then somebody is to free themselves from
suffering yeah so it's uh the other
thing I would say it's it's
um it's a matter as well of uh
repetition like you know you you have
the you have the intellectual kind of
reasoning and and reading the sutas and
so on and you here that yes there is a
difference between these two things but
um you have to keep in mind like
for as long as I'm still for as long as
there's any degree of uncertainty and
doubt that's why authenticity is so
important for as long as there is any
liability to
to
um for as long as you feel again you're
enslaved you're you're you're imprisoned
and that and and you're not entirely
sure whether you're going to be able to
get out well that means even though yes
the idea makes sense you haven't
actually understood it concretely to the
point where like those hindrances would
cease to be hindrances in that sense so
um that's why like you know with with
the whole contemporary meditation
approaches and so on people feel like
yeah you know they're freeing themselves
from these hindrances but at the end of
the day because there's that that lack
of authenticity to
recognize actually I'm still liable to
them like know the only reason why I'm
able to sort of um
seemingly get out of the prison cell is
because like you know the circumstances
are are suitable for it there's somebody
outside who's helping me get out but I
don't actually have the key where where
I could get out at will and that's when
people would realize you know if they
precious daily setup of meditation two
hours a day and and bunch of other
external factors were to were to be lost
then they wouldn't anymore be able to
overcome the hindrances so that's why
it's uh crucial to keep in mind that um
that uh freedom from
doubt is like that's really the criteria
I mean because doubt is one of the
hindrances as well yes so uh that's
that's uh the criteria to be able to see
whether you actually understood it or
not and um you can have like as many
sort of experiences as you want where it
seems like everything is Cal and so on
but uh as it says it's it's it's when
you understand how these things come to
be how they don't come to be how they're
abandoned that's when you actually
purify yourself it doesn't say like what
is mental Purity here aiku doesn't have
Central desire because that can happen
like actually there's another suta where
I think we mentioned that one before
where it says um the five lower Freds I
think that's majima 64 and then this
monk just list lists them out kind of in
the superficial sense and the Buddha
says well if those were the five lower
feds then your baby would be free from
them because the baby doesn't know what
of any s desires there that Sim
in I think yeah yeah he doesn't know
what sensal desires are he doesn't know
what so like just not having these
things that doesn't mean anything yeah
so because that's the underlying
Tendencies and and so when we speak
about liability that's the level we're
talking about like these underlying
Tendencies are still there yeah and and
basically you could frame those
underlying Tendencies is okay right now
um so what's the difference between then
not having the underlying tendency and
having it it's like well what would
happen if my state of mind were to
deteriorate mhm um what what if I were
to lose a pleasant de bodying because
again many people operate with the
assumption that that should never happen
but this are not that's not what this to
say so
um if you know you're mind that internal
environment even your internal external
environment you're able to kind of cope
with difficulties and so on but if in
your internal environment your own mind
that's not yours your five arat they get
out of whack would you now
suffer and uh cuz you know there's
millions of things that can even on the
bodily level like if if
somebody uh put certain substances in
your body or something you know things
can happen happen to to your mental
state so uh underlying tendency has been
actually removed when no matter what
happens to that internal environment in
the same way as the external environment
doesn't disturb you well that wouldn't
disturb you either because you fully
understood that the five Aggregates are
not yours and the qualification to make
as well
is um any of the actions that happen on
the external level like you know as as
it says in cabus all the things that the
S to say Anar Hunt is Inc capable of um
those things wouldn't have like those
things would be inconceivable even
though the mental state that for an
ordinary person would have led to them
yes can still be there in its sort of
outlines as I said um so just to clear
up that people don't think like an arand
would go around doing whatever they want
because no the thing is you cannot do
those actions unless you appropriate
your mental state CU like I know I'm not
taking up my my my Essential desire but
I'm still having sexual intercourse like
some people would say yeah because you
know it's anata or or whatever no these
are actions that if you do them you took
up the ownership of your mental state of
your CH automatically you acted out
externally you were not pure if you if
you did those actions but everything in
between like you know when the suas
would say um kind of a Sometimes some
wouldn't be recognized in the sutas like
on account of oh because he was a with
bad families or whatever uh it doesn't
mean that he was doing anything like
against the precepts or whatnot but
somebody else who was maybe more
composed uh you know another another
Monk or something saw that then he
thought well he was in doubt about the
fact that he was narun and then the
Buddha actually told him no actually he
is and I say what's actually blameworthy
is to take up another body yes that
you're craving so um but it's it doesn't
mean that like he would have been you
know breaking rules and going around
that because those things
are necessarily done out of ownership